<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>jcsherin</title>
	<subtitle>jcsherin writes about programming</subtitle>
	
	<link href="https://jacobsherin.com/feed/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="https://jacobsherin.com/"/>
	<updated>2025-04-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
	<id>https://example.com/</id>
	<author>
		<name>Your Name Here</name>
		<email>youremailaddress@example.com</email>
	</author>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Nested Record Shredding</title>
		<link href="https://jacobsherin.com/posts/dremel-column-striping/"/>
		<updated>2025-04-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://jacobsherin.com/posts/dremel-column-striping/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Introduction &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;https://jacobsherin.com/posts/dremel-column-striping/#introduction&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main issue with flattening nested data structures is ensuring the&lt;br /&gt;
process is reversible. The flattened representation needs to contain both data&lt;br /&gt;
and the metadata which encodes the structure. From this representation, one&lt;br /&gt;
should be able to correctly reconstruct the original nested data structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, a query reads only a few attributes. Therefore, it is more&lt;br /&gt;
efficient to read only those specific attributes, rather than the entire&lt;br /&gt;
nested data structure. Consequently, a core desirable property of&lt;br /&gt;
such flattening is the ability to partially reconstruct the nested data&lt;br /&gt;
structure, skipping any attributes not mentioned in the query.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[ ] &lt;strong&gt;TODO:&lt;/strong&gt; Create illustration for partial projection
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective:&lt;/strong&gt; Original and partial side by side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Details&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clear, compact (YAML over JSON)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example has 2 or more levels of nesting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearly labelled as original&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partial Projection&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Briefly state the query (e.g. query for product id and English(US)&lt;br /&gt;
description of first image)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show the result partial projection from original&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearly labelled as partial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Placement:&lt;/strong&gt; Insert after paragraph discussing partial reconstruction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;data-model&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Data Model &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;https://jacobsherin.com/posts/dremel-column-striping/#data-model&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a moment consider a nested data model with the following restrictions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All fields are mandatory. There are never any null values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This model disallows list or array types, permitting only struct types and&lt;br /&gt;
scalar types (includes integers, floating-point, boolean, characters and&lt;br /&gt;
strings).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we do not have to explicitly track field presence because no field can&lt;br /&gt;
ever be null. Furthermore, since all fields are mandatory and this model&lt;br /&gt;
disallows lists (meaning each field is a single scalar or struct, not a&lt;br /&gt;
collection), the cardinality of every field is exactly one. Consequently, we&lt;br /&gt;
do not have to determine if a list is empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In such a model, the structure of any data instance perfectly mirrors its&lt;br /&gt;
schema. Consequently, the schema alone is sufficient to reconstruct the&lt;br /&gt;
original nested data structure from its flattened representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[ ] &lt;strong&gt;TODO:&lt;/strong&gt; Concrete example with a nested value + schema&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These restrictions limit our ability to represent most real-world nested&lt;br /&gt;
datasets. But at the same time, this simplified model demonstrates which&lt;br /&gt;
structural properties must be encoded as metadata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is an optional field present or not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is a list empty or not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In columnar storage values of a single column attribute are stored&lt;br /&gt;
contiguously. In analytics databases the query optimizer can apply&lt;br /&gt;
projection pushdown directly to the data source. This means only those columns&lt;br /&gt;
which are specified in the query are read from storage. Analytical queries are&lt;br /&gt;
often aggregations over the entire data source. So this can reduce the I/O&lt;br /&gt;
required and make the queries run faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to map flat relational data to columns. Given a projection of&lt;br /&gt;
columns the original record can be reassembled by index or offset. A record&lt;br /&gt;
has the same index or offset across all columns. This is not the case with&lt;br /&gt;
nested data structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If nested data structures can be shredded into columns, then it is possible&lt;br /&gt;
to use a SQL or DataFrame interface to query nested data. All the built-in&lt;br /&gt;
optimizations which are available for relational data also then becomes&lt;br /&gt;
available to nested data structures. The ability to interactively query millions&lt;br /&gt;
or billions of nested data becomes possible in a single node using a vectorized&lt;br /&gt;
query execution engines like DuckDB, ClickHouse or Apache DataFusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# First record
ProductId: 123
ImageGallery:
  PrimaryImageId: 555
  AdditionalImageId:
    - 556
    - 557

# Second record
ProductId: 678
ImageGallery:
  PrimaryImageId: 987
  AdditionalImageId:
    - 988
    - 989
    - 990
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nested data structures are tree shaped. The atomic or primitive value is&lt;br /&gt;
found at the leaf of the tree. And columns in the nested data structure is&lt;br /&gt;
the path from root to leaf. The columns with their data type are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ProductId - Integer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ImageGallery.PrimaryImageId - Integer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId - Array[Integer]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two records above after being shredded into column values will look like&lt;br /&gt;
this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ProductId                       : [123, 678]
ImageGallery.PrimaryImageId     : [555, 987]
ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId  : [556, 557, 988, 989, 990]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the absence of other metadata it is now impossible for us to reassemble&lt;br /&gt;
the original records. The structural information is lost with this encoding.&lt;br /&gt;
We are unable to identify where a record begins or ends when the nested data&lt;br /&gt;
structure contains repeated (array) values. In this representation it is not&lt;br /&gt;
possible anymore to know which values in &lt;code&gt;ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
belongs to which records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# First record
ProductId: 123
ImageGallery:
  PrimaryImageId: 555
  AdditionalImageId:
    - 556
    - 557
AltText:
  - Language:
      - Locale: en-US
        Description: Athletic running shoes
        Keyword:
          - shoes
          - running
          - athletic

# Second record
ProductId: 678
ImageGallery:
  PrimaryImageId: 987
  AdditionalImageId:
    - 988
    - 989
    - 990
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real world nested data structures are also sparse. In this example the&lt;br /&gt;
first nested data contains descriptive text columns, but the second record&lt;br /&gt;
does not. For partially or completely missing paths in a nested data&lt;br /&gt;
structure NULL values are inserted. The more sparse the data because of&lt;br /&gt;
missing column values, the more NULL values there will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ProductId                       : [123, 678]
ImageGallery.PrimaryImageId     : [555, 987]
ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId  : [556, 557, 988, 989, 990]

# Columns present only in the first record
AltText.Language.Locale         : [&amp;quot;en-US&amp;quot;, NULL]
AltText.Language.Description    : [&amp;quot;Athletic running shoes&amp;quot;, NULL]
AltText.Language.Keyword        : [&amp;quot;shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;running&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;athletic&amp;quot;, NULL]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dremel (Google BigQuery) paper (VLDB 2010) introduced a new&lt;br /&gt;
representation for nested data in columnar storage which also stored the&lt;br /&gt;
structural hierarchy of the nested data side by side with the column values.&lt;br /&gt;
This metadata made it possible to reassemble the original nested data&lt;br /&gt;
structure back from columnar format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ability to represent nested data directly in a columnar format meant&lt;br /&gt;
increased developer productivity. There is no need to normalize the nested&lt;br /&gt;
data by extracting entities and joining multiple relations using foreign&lt;br /&gt;
keys in some star or snowflake schema for data analysis. Developers could&lt;br /&gt;
use the SQL query execution for interactive analysis of very large nested&lt;br /&gt;
datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later when Parquet was created it added ground up support nested data&lt;br /&gt;
structures in its file format using the techniques and principles described&lt;br /&gt;
in the Dremel paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;code&gt;ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId&lt;/code&gt; it was impossible to reassemble the&lt;br /&gt;
original two records by looking at only the stored column values. In Dremel&lt;br /&gt;
they introduced metadata which encodes the structure of the values in the&lt;br /&gt;
nested data. They are definition level and repetition level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the below example by reading &lt;code&gt;d&lt;/code&gt; (definition level) and &lt;code&gt;r&lt;/code&gt; (repetition&lt;br /&gt;
level) in tandem with the column values the original nested values can be&lt;br /&gt;
reassembled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId Column

d       : [1, 1, 1, 1, 1]             # definition level
r       : [0, 1, 0, 1, 1]             # repetition level
values  : [556, 557, 988, 989, 990]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To compute the definition level of &lt;code&gt;ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId&lt;/code&gt; we need&lt;br /&gt;
to count all the optional and repeated fields in it. To compute the&lt;br /&gt;
repetition level the index of the value must be known. If there are multiple&lt;br /&gt;
repeated fields in column path, then the computed repetition level of the&lt;br /&gt;
nearest repeated ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The schema of the nested data is required for us to know if a field is&lt;br /&gt;
defined as required, optional or repeated. So let us inspect the schema for&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;ProductImages&lt;/code&gt; document before formalizing the computation of definition&lt;br /&gt;
and repetition levels from the nested data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The schema for &lt;code&gt;ProductImages&lt;/code&gt; is given below. From the schema we can see that&lt;br /&gt;
this is a nested document which contains the display images for a product and&lt;br /&gt;
language translations of the image descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data model is,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A field is either a struct type or a primitive type like an integer,&lt;br /&gt;
string, float, boolean etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A field with no explicit multiplicity labels is a required field. A&lt;br /&gt;
required field will always be present in the nested data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An optional field is explicitly marked in the schema. In nested data this&lt;br /&gt;
field maybe present or absent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A repeated field is represented as an array of values. The type of&lt;br /&gt;
repeated field can be either a struct type or a primitive type.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ordering of repeated values is significant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The leaf node is always a primitive type, or a repeated field of a&lt;br /&gt;
primitive type.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A column name is represented using dot notation by joining the field names&lt;br /&gt;
from root to leaf. Eg. &lt;code&gt;AltText.Language.Keyword&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ProductImages                     # Document Name
├─ ProductId [int64]
├─ ImageGallery
│  ├─ PrimaryImageId [int64]
│  └─ AdditionalImageId [int64]*  # repeated
└─ AltText?                       # optional
   └─ Language*                   # repeated
      ├─ Locale [string]
      ├─ Description [string]?    # optional
      └─ Keyword [string]*        # repeated

* = repeated
? = optional
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A definition level for a column value is computed by counting the occurrence&lt;br /&gt;
of optional and repeated fields which are present in the value. If an optional&lt;br /&gt;
field is absent then we do not increment the definition level. If a repeated&lt;br /&gt;
field is empty or missing we do not increment the definition level. So the&lt;br /&gt;
definition level can tell us where the path in a tree terminated for any&lt;br /&gt;
given column value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is not enough for us to reassemble repeated values. The repetition&lt;br /&gt;
level is used to identify the beginning of an array from the rest of the&lt;br /&gt;
array values. For computing repetition levels, only repeated fields in a&lt;br /&gt;
path are counted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ImageGallery&lt;/code&gt; is a required field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;AdditionalImageId&lt;/code&gt; is a repeated field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId Column

definition_levels : [1, 1, 1, 1, 1]
repetition_levels : [0, 1, 0, 1, 1]
values            : [556, 557, 988, 989, 990]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the definition levels we can see that for all values the path is&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;ImageGallery.AdditionalImageId&lt;/code&gt; because the definition level is 1 which&lt;br /&gt;
means the repeated field &lt;code&gt;AdditionalImageId&lt;/code&gt; in the path is always present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is only a single repeated field, so the repetition levels can be&lt;br /&gt;
either zero or one. To identify the start of the array, the first element in&lt;br /&gt;
this example will have a repetition level of zero. The remaining values in&lt;br /&gt;
the array will have the repetition level of one. So &lt;code&gt;556&lt;/code&gt; has repetition level&lt;br /&gt;
of zero, and &lt;code&gt;557&lt;/code&gt; has a repetition level of one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next value &lt;code&gt;988&lt;/code&gt; we can infer that it belongs to the second record&lt;br /&gt;
because it has a repetition level of zero. This means it has to be the first&lt;br /&gt;
value in the array. And the remaining values in the second record &lt;code&gt;989&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;989&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
because they have a repetition level of 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example we were able to identify that the repeated values belonged&lt;br /&gt;
to two separate nested values using the repetition levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next let us look at a example which contains null values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ProductId: 123
ImageGallery:
  PrimaryImageId: 555
  AdditionalImageId:
    - 556
    - 557
AltText:
  - Language:
      - Locale: en-US
        Description: Athletic running shoes
        Keyword:
          - shoes
          - athletic
  - Language:
      - Locale: en-GB
        Description: Athletic trainers
        Keyword:
          - trainers
          - sport
  - Language:
      - Locale: fr-FR
  - Language:
      - Locale: de-DE
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The column &lt;code&gt;AltText.Language.Description&lt;/code&gt; contains a repeated field and&lt;br /&gt;
exactly two optional fields. The definition level therefore can be between 0&lt;br /&gt;
and 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AltText: optional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Language: repeated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Description: optional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After compiling the column values, there are two NULL values. This&lt;br /&gt;
represents the missing &lt;code&gt;Description&lt;/code&gt; in the 2nd and 3rd &lt;code&gt;Language&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
repetition which corresponds to the &lt;code&gt;Locale&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;fr-FR&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;de-DE&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# AltText.Language.Description Column

values: [&amp;quot;Athletic running shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Athletic trainers&amp;quot;, NULL, NULL]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next let us compute the definition levels. The definition level for both the&lt;br /&gt;
NULL values is two because the path terminates at &lt;code&gt;AltText.Language&lt;/code&gt; as the&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Description&lt;/code&gt; field is missing in both cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# AltText.Language.Description Column

definition_levels : [3, 3, 2, 2]
values            : [&amp;quot;Athletic running shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Athletic trainers&amp;quot;, NULL, NULL]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next let us compute the repetition levels. This column has a single repeated&lt;br /&gt;
field which is &lt;code&gt;Language&lt;/code&gt;. So repetition levels will be between 0 and 1 for&lt;br /&gt;
all values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here the repetition level of zero clearly identifies the first element in&lt;br /&gt;
the repeated field &lt;code&gt;Language&lt;/code&gt;, from the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# AltText.Language.Description Column

repetition_levels : [0, 1, 1, 1]
definition_levels : [3, 3, 2, 2]
values            : [&amp;quot;Athletic running shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Athletic trainers&amp;quot;, NULL, NULL]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next let us look at an example where there is more than one repeated field&lt;br /&gt;
in a column. The &lt;code&gt;AltText.Language.Keyword&lt;/code&gt; column has two repeated fields&lt;br /&gt;
and a single optional field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us compile the values first. The final two NULL values represent the&lt;br /&gt;
missing &lt;code&gt;Keyword&lt;/code&gt; in the second and third repetition of &lt;code&gt;Language&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# AltText.Language.Keywords

values: [&amp;quot;shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;athletic&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;trainers&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sport&amp;quot;, NULL, NULL]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next let us compute the definition levels. The NULL values have a definition&lt;br /&gt;
level of two because &lt;code&gt;Keyword&lt;/code&gt; field is missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# AltText.Language.Keyword

values: [&amp;quot;shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;athletic&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;trainers&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sport&amp;quot;, NULL, NULL]
def   : [3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 2]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next let us compute the repetition levels. This looks complicated, but you&lt;br /&gt;
will soon see how this exactly reassembles the original nested data structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# AltText.Language.Keyword

values: [&amp;quot;shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;athletic&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;trainers&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sport&amp;quot;, NULL, NULL]
def   : [3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 2]
rep   : [0, 2, 1, 2, 1, 1]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us look at the nested column in isolation and give it index numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;AltText:
  - Language:         # Language[0]
        - Keyword:
          - shoes     # Language[0].Keyword[0]
          - athletic  # Language[0].Keyword[0]
  - Language:         # Language[1]
        - Keyword:
          - trainers  # Language[1].Keyword[0]
          - sport     # Language[1].Keyword[1]
  - Language:         # Language[2]
  - Language:         # Language[3]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two repeated fields &lt;code&gt;Alt.Language.Keyword&lt;/code&gt; which are &lt;code&gt;Language&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
and then &lt;code&gt;Keyword&lt;/code&gt;. So values in this column may have repetition levels - 0,&lt;br /&gt;
1 or 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complete path for &lt;code&gt;shoes&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;Language[0].Keyword[0]&lt;/code&gt;. This value is the&lt;br /&gt;
first repeated value in the path of this nested data structure. The&lt;br /&gt;
repetition level of &lt;code&gt;Language[0]&lt;/code&gt; is zero. The repetition level of &lt;code&gt;Keyword [0]&lt;/code&gt; is also zero. It inherits the repetition level of the nearest repeated&lt;br /&gt;
ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second value is &lt;code&gt;athletic&lt;/code&gt; with path &lt;code&gt;Language[0].Keyword[1]&lt;/code&gt;. The&lt;br /&gt;
computed repetition level is two so that we can distinctly identify that&lt;br /&gt;
this is not the first item in &lt;code&gt;Keyword&lt;/code&gt;. Because this is not the first item&lt;br /&gt;
we do not have to consider the repetition level of a repeated ancestor. Here&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Keyword&lt;/code&gt; field is the second repeated field of this column which is present&lt;br /&gt;
and therefore the repetition level is two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third value is &lt;code&gt;trainers&lt;/code&gt;. It has the path &lt;code&gt;Language[1].Keyword[0]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Even though this is the first Keyword, it is the second repetition of&lt;br /&gt;
Language. So the repetition level of &lt;code&gt;Language[1]&lt;/code&gt; is one. And since it is&lt;br /&gt;
the first keyword, we inherit that value. So the computed repetition level&lt;br /&gt;
is one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth value is &lt;code&gt;sport&lt;/code&gt; and the path is &lt;code&gt;Language[1].Keyword[1]&lt;/code&gt;. The&lt;br /&gt;
computed repetition level is two here. This is the second keyword, and so&lt;br /&gt;
the repetition level is same as the number of repeated fields in this path&lt;br /&gt;
which happens to be two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fifth and sixth values are both NULL. They have the paths &lt;code&gt;Language[2]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;Language[3]&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;Keyword&lt;/code&gt; field is empty or missing. So we compute&lt;br /&gt;
the repetition level up to &lt;code&gt;Language&lt;/code&gt; field. And the value is one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# AltText.Language.Keyword

values: [&amp;quot;shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;athletic&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;trainers&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sport&amp;quot;, NULL, NULL]
def   : [3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 2]
rep   : [0, 2, 1, 2, 1, 1]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we know how definition and repetition levels are computed, it is&lt;br /&gt;
possible to reassemble the nested data structure from the column values,&lt;br /&gt;
definition and repetition levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the column storage values we can also reassemble a partial projection of&lt;br /&gt;
the nested data structure in its original form. For example if only the&lt;br /&gt;
following columns are selected - [ProductId, AltText.Language.Locale] which&lt;br /&gt;
is stored in columnar format as,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ProductId Column
values            : [123, 456]
definition_level  : [0, 0]
repetition_level  : [0, 0]

# AltText.Language.Locale
values            : [&#39;en-US&#39;, &#39;en-GB&#39;, &#39;fr-FR&#39;, &#39;de-DE&#39;, NULL]
definition_level  : [2, 2, 2, 2, 0]
repetition_level  : [0, 1, 1, 1, 0]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reassembled nested data structure resembles the original but contains&lt;br /&gt;
only the selected columns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Record 1
ProductId: 123
AltText:
  - Language:
      - Locale: en-US
  - Language:
      - Locale: en-GB
  - Language:
      - Locale: fr-FR
  - Language:
      - Locale: de-DE

# Record 2
ProductId: 678
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just a physical representation. In physical storage the NULL values&lt;br /&gt;
can be omitted. Because we know that for the column &lt;code&gt;AltText.Language. Keyword&lt;/code&gt; has a max definition level of 3. It has an optional field &lt;code&gt;AltText&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
and two repeated fields &lt;code&gt;Language&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Keyword&lt;/code&gt;. So when we see a&lt;br /&gt;
definition level value lower than 3, we know that it stands for a NULL value.&lt;br /&gt;
This way we can avoid storing the NULL values. This is a useful property for&lt;br /&gt;
real world nested data structures which are sparse, and therefore has many&lt;br /&gt;
NULL values need not be physically stored saving space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# AltText.Language.Keyword

# Logical representation
# values: [&amp;quot;shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;athletic&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;trainers&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sport&amp;quot;, NULL, NULL]

# Physical representation which does not store NULL values
values: [&amp;quot;shoes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;athletic&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;trainers&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sport&amp;quot;]
def   : [3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 2]
rep   : [0, 2, 1, 2, 1, 1]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example &lt;code&gt;ProductId&lt;/code&gt; is a required field so there is no need to store&lt;br /&gt;
the definition levels. The definition level is always zero for all values.&lt;br /&gt;
Similarly, a definition level of zero implies that the repetition level is&lt;br /&gt;
also zero. So we do not also need to store repetition levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ProductId Column
values            : [123, 456]
definition_level  : [0, 0]
repetition_level  : [0, 0]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this encoding in physical storage we only write the column values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ProductId Column
values            : [123, 456]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draft Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve definition level explanation: counting number of optional and&lt;br /&gt;
repeated fields in the path from root to where the value is found, or&lt;br /&gt;
where the path terminates for NULL values or paths which are entirely&lt;br /&gt;
missing which can happen if the first field in a path is optional and&lt;br /&gt;
therefore is a NULL value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;code&gt;AltText.Language.Keyword&lt;/code&gt; the computation of repetition levels needs&lt;br /&gt;
improvement. For e.g. in the case of &amp;quot;athletic&amp;quot; the second repeated field&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Keyword&lt;/code&gt; is repeating, therefore the repetition level switches from zero&lt;br /&gt;
to two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The path with index &lt;code&gt;Language[0].Keyword[1]&lt;/code&gt; for demonstrating the&lt;br /&gt;
relationship with repetition levels can be compiled as a table or a nested&lt;br /&gt;
list. The key is to explicitly outline the repetition level no matter&lt;br /&gt;
which format is used for visualizing the relationship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A definition level less than maximum value means a NULL value at that&lt;br /&gt;
specific position in the schema. The count provides clues as to where the&lt;br /&gt;
path terminated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add visual diagrams like in the Twitter blog post - Dremel made simple&lt;br /&gt;
with Parquet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include an example of a flat schema with a required, optional and repeated&lt;br /&gt;
field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include bit-level packing of definition, repetition levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The twitter blog post includes examples of how useful data structures like&lt;br /&gt;
map (key, value) are implemented. It maybe useful to show the separation&lt;br /&gt;
between logical and physical types. Map is a logical type which is&lt;br /&gt;
rewritten to a struct physical type with a required key of type string,&lt;br /&gt;
and an optional value of a primitive type or a record type.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The twitter blog post also includes a nested list example for&lt;br /&gt;
demonstrating repetition levels. I need to reference it again to check how&lt;br /&gt;
it is represented logically similar to the map type.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include a couple of practical SQL query examples over the column&lt;br /&gt;
shredded nested data structures using Apache DataFusion. The test data can&lt;br /&gt;
be generated and written using python to Parquet format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parquet precomputed offset index which helps with deeply nested&lt;br /&gt;
documents where otherwise we have to scan the definition, repetition&lt;br /&gt;
levels from beginning to end to jump to a record. Include a concrete&lt;br /&gt;
example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include record reassembly as a separate example instead of merging it with&lt;br /&gt;
the explanation of definition, and repetition levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schema merging in Parquet. Include an example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In proto3 there is a significant change. Fields are optional by default&lt;br /&gt;
and need not be marked as optional. They don&#39;t use the optional keyword&lt;br /&gt;
anymore. The paper uses the proto2 syntax and semantics. The optional&lt;br /&gt;
fields are explicitly marked. So proto3 removed required fields and uses&lt;br /&gt;
default values for missing fields instead of explicitly tracking presence.&lt;br /&gt;
This means it is not possible anymore to identify if a field which was&lt;br /&gt;
explicitly set to default value vs one which was not set at all. But this&lt;br /&gt;
change was included to make it possible to mark an optional field as&lt;br /&gt;
required (dangerous) made it challenging for schema evolution. But proto3&lt;br /&gt;
reintroduced the optional keyword again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include concrete SQL example for predicate pushdown.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include Zero-Copy Optimization when reading from Parquet to Arrow.&lt;br /&gt;
Remapping definition levels to validity bitmaps, and repetition levels to&lt;br /&gt;
offset indexes. The last entry (n+1 for n items) indicates position after&lt;br /&gt;
the last element. This also has to do with point access when you want to&lt;br /&gt;
read all the values for record N, you can do offset[N-1] - offset[N] and&lt;br /&gt;
directly read only those values from offset[N-1].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not a post about light-weight compression schemes, so I am not&lt;br /&gt;
adding anything about dictionary encoding, run-length encoding etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predicate Pushdown for Nested Fields - Concrete Example&lt;br /&gt;
Consider a schema with nested e-commerce orders:&lt;br /&gt;
Order&lt;br /&gt;
├─ OrderId&lt;br /&gt;
├─ Customer&lt;br /&gt;
│ ├─ CustomerId&lt;br /&gt;
│ ├─ Name&lt;br /&gt;
│ └─ PremiumStatus&lt;br /&gt;
└─ Items [array]&lt;br /&gt;
├─ ProductId&lt;br /&gt;
├─ Quantity&lt;br /&gt;
└─ Price&lt;br /&gt;
Let&#39;s say we want all orders where any item has a price over $100:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-sql&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sql&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;SELECT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;FROM&lt;/span&gt; orders&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;WHERE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;EXISTS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;SELECT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;FROM&lt;/span&gt; UNNEST&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;items&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;WHERE&lt;/span&gt; price &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional Approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read all columns for all Order records&lt;br /&gt;
Reconstruct the full nested structure&lt;br /&gt;
Apply the filter to each record&lt;br /&gt;
Return matching records&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predicate Pushdown with Nested Fields:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The query engine identifies that only the Items.Price column needs examining&lt;br /&gt;
first&lt;br /&gt;
It reads only the Items.Price column with its definition and repetition levels&lt;br /&gt;
It creates a bitmap of which Orders have at least one item with price &amp;gt; $100&lt;br /&gt;
It then only reads the remaining columns for Orders that matched the filter&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a dataset with 1 million orders but only 5% having items over $100, this&lt;br /&gt;
approach reads only 5% of the data for most columns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>This is my fourth post.</title>
		<link href="https://jacobsherin.com/posts/fourthpost/"/>
		<updated>2018-09-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://jacobsherin.com/posts/fourthpost/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Leverage agile frameworks to provide a robust synopsis for high level overviews. Iterative approaches to corporate strategy foster collaborative thinking to further the overall value proposition. Organically grow the holistic world view of disruptive innovation via workplace diversity and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-header&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Section Header &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;https://jacobsherin.com/posts/fourthpost/#section-header&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on low hanging fruit to identify a ballpark value added activity to beta test. Override the digital divide with additional clickthroughs from DevOps. Nanotechnology immersion along the information highway will close the loop on focusing solely on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>This is my third post.</title>
		<link href="https://jacobsherin.com/posts/thirdpost/"/>
		<updated>2018-08-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://jacobsherin.com/posts/thirdpost/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Leverage agile frameworks to provide a robust synopsis for high level overviews. Iterative approaches to corporate strategy foster collaborative thinking to further the overall value proposition. Organically grow the holistic world view of disruptive innovation via workplace diversity and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-diff-js&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-diff-js&quot;&gt;// this is a command&lt;br /&gt;function myCommand() {&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token inserted-sign inserted language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix inserted&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; counter &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token deleted-sign deleted language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix deleted&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;	counter&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;// Test with a line break above this line.&lt;br /&gt;console.log(&#39;Test&#39;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-header&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Section Header &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;https://jacobsherin.com/posts/thirdpost/#section-header&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on low hanging fruit to identify a ballpark value added activity to beta test. Override the digital divide with additional clickthroughs from DevOps. Nanotechnology immersion along the information highway will close the loop on focusing solely on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>This is my second post.</title>
		<link href="https://jacobsherin.com/posts/secondpost/"/>
		<updated>2018-07-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://jacobsherin.com/posts/secondpost/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Leverage agile frameworks to provide a robust synopsis for high level overviews. Iterative approaches to corporate strategy foster collaborative thinking to further the overall value proposition. Organically grow the holistic world view of disruptive innovation via workplace diversity and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-header&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Section Header &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;https://jacobsherin.com/posts/secondpost/#section-header&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jacobsherin.com/posts/firstpost/&quot;&gt;First post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://jacobsherin.com/posts/thirdpost/&quot;&gt;Third post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on low hanging fruit to identify a ballpark value added activity to beta test. Override the digital divide with additional clickthroughs from DevOps. Nanotechnology immersion along the information highway will close the loop on focusing solely on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>This is my first post.</title>
		<link href="https://jacobsherin.com/posts/firstpost/"/>
		<updated>2018-05-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://jacobsherin.com/posts/firstpost/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Leverage agile frameworks to provide a robust synopsis for high level overviews. Iterative approaches to corporate strategy foster collaborative thinking to further the overall value proposition. Organically grow the holistic world view of disruptive innovation via workplace diversity and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-header&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Section Header &lt;a class=&quot;direct-link&quot; href=&quot;https://jacobsherin.com/posts/firstpost/#section-header&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on low hanging fruit to identify a ballpark value added activity to beta test. Override the digital divide with additional clickthroughs from DevOps. Nanotechnology immersion along the information highway will close the loop on focusing solely on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-diff-js&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-diff-js&quot;&gt;// this is a command&lt;br /&gt;function myCommand() {&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token inserted-sign inserted language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix inserted&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; counter &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token prefix inserted&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;	counter&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;// Test with a line break above this line.&lt;br /&gt;console.log(&#39;Test&#39;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
